Herbert Aach
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Herbert Aach papers
1942-1988
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Aach, Herbert
2.4 linear feet
The papers of New York painter, art instructor and writer Herbert Aach (1923-1985) measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1942 to 1988. Papers include biographical materials, correspondence, scattered financial and legal records, notes and writings, subject files, a scrapbook, printed materials, photographs, and one videocassette.
Provenance
Herbert and Doris Aach donated the papers to the Archives of American Art in 1984 and 1989.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Painter, art instructor and writer Herbert Aach (1923-1985) worked primarily in New York City. Born in Cologne, Germany, Aach came to the United States in 1939. He taught at the Brooklyn Museum School (1947-1951), Pratt Institute (1966-1969), and at Queens College (1966-1985). In 1971 he was editor and translator of Goethe's Color Theory. Aach was president of the Artists Technical Research Institute, which was founded in 1959 by Bena Frank and Ralph Mayer to conduct scientific and educational research of materials and methods used in the visual arts.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York painter, art instructor and writer Herbert Aach (1923-1985) measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1942 to 1988. Papers include biographical materials, correspondence, scattered financial and legal records, notes and writings, subject files, a scrapbook, printed materials, photographs, and one videocassette.
Legal records include materials relating to a lawsuit against Larry Rivers for a lease termination. Letters are from colleagues including Emily Genauer and Edwin W. Zoller regarding exhibitions and other art-related matters and brief letters from Elaine DeKooning, John Ferren, Adolph Gottlieb, and Rufino Tamayo. Subject files are found for many organizations of which Aach was a member, including the American Society for Testing and Materials, the Artists Technical Research Institute, and the Inter-Society Color Council. Printed materials include one scrapbook, clippings, and exhibition catalogs. There is documentation of Aach's work translating and editing Goethe's Color Theory, one 55 minute videocassette entitled Herbert Aach by Albright Knox Gallery, and photographs of Aach and his artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series. Records are generally arranged by material type and chronologically thereafter.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1985 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1949-1988 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Financial Material, 1964-1981 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 4: Legal Records, 1951-1986 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Notes, 1961-1984 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 6: Writings, 1950-1985(Boxes 1-2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Subject Files, 1942-1984 (Box 2; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1952-1960 (Box 2; 3 folders)
Series 9: Scrapbook, 1951-1958 (Box 2; 1 folder)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1948-1988 (Boxes 2-3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Videocassette, 25 April 1975 (Box 3; 1 folder)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Rivers, Larry, 1925-2002; De Kooning, Elaine; Ferren, John, 1905-1970; Genauer, Emily, 1910-; Tamayo, Rufino, 1899-; Zoller, Edwin W., 1900-1967; American Society for Testing and Materials; Artist's Technical Research Institute; Inter-Society Color Council
Subjects-Topical:
Artists' materials; Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Video recordings; Scrapbooks
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1985, Series 1:
  Biographical materials include a resume, exhibition records and three biographical essays about Aach.
  - Biographical Material, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1949-1988, Series 2:
  Correspondence is primarily between Aach and various art suppliers and chemical analysis laboratories concerning the technical standards for artists' materials. Also included are letters from colleagues including Emily Genauer and Edwin W. Zoller regarding exhibitions and other art-related matters and brief letters from Elaine DeKooning, John Ferren, Adolph Gottlieb, and Rufino Tamayo agreeing to write recommendations for Aach.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1988, (27 folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-29)
- Financial Material, 1964-1981, Series 3:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Financial material includes a grant proposal to study the serialization and color programming of Gothic rose windows, a price list for fluorochemical additives, and four invoices for the sale of paintings and for supplies.
  - Financial Records, 1964-1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Legal Records, 1951-1986, Series 4:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  Legal records include two contracts with the Creative Gallery, consignment agreements, and material relating to a law suit against Larry Rivers concerning the termination of Aach's lease on his studio.
  - Contracts with Creative Gallery and Consignment Agreements, 1951-1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Loft Lease, Aach v. Rivers, 1980-1981, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
  - Transcript of examination before trial, Aach v. Rivers, 1984, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
  - Loft Lease, Aach v. Rivers, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Notes, 1961-1984, Series 5:; (Box 1; 6 folders)
  Notes include technical data on paint, exhibition guest registers, and a notebook with outlines for classes taught at Queen's College.
  - Notebook for Color, Design Class, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Queens College Notebook, circa 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Color Course at Queens College, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Data on Paint, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Exhibition Guest Registers, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
- Writings, 1950-1985, Series 6:; (Boxes 1-2; 0.2 linear feet)
  Writings include texts for lectures, miscellaneous writings by Aach on art techniques and materials, evaluations by students, Gail O'Brien's master's thesis entitled "The Painter's Approach Toward Serialization in Modern Painting", and information about printmaking by Jack Stewart.
  - Lecture Notes, undated, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Evaluations by Students, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1950-1981, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
  - Printmaking Information by Jack Stewart, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Masters Thesis: The Painter's Approach toward Serialization in Modern Painting by Gail O'Brien, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Subject Files, 1942-1984, Series 7:; (Box 2; 0.6 linear feet)
  Subject files contain letters, notes, and printed material concerning the American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM), the Artists Technical Research Insitute, Inc. (ATRI), the Color Forum, the International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX), the Inter-Society Color Council (ISCC), New York Bridges, and the "Structure of Color" exhibition at the Whitney Museum. Also included is the book Goethe's Color Theory, which is translated and edited by Aach. The ATRI file contains correspondence between Ralph and Bena Frank Mayer, Ralston Crawford, Rutherford J. Gettens, and others concerning the establishment of ATRI, a copy of the by-laws, technical reports, and minutes of meetings.
  - American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM) Subcommittee D01.57, 1977- 1982, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-14)
  - By-Laws of ATRI Inc. / Certificate of Incorporation of ATRI Inc., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Minutes of ATRI Meetings, 1960-1978 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings and Articles Regarding Artists Technical Research Institute and Paint Standards, undated, 1957- 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - ATRI, 1942-1981, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - Color Forum, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Goethe Book, 1970-1983, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
  - International Research and Exchanges Board, 1979-1984, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Inter-Society Color Council (ISCC) Subcommittee 37, 1971-1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - New York Bridges, 1981-1982, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - The "Structure of Color" Exhibition at the Whitney, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Photographs, 1952-1960, Series 8:; (Box 2; 3 folders)
  The photographs are of Aach and of his works of art.
  - Photographs of Aach, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
- Scrapbook, 1951-1958, Series 9:; (Box 2; 1 folder)
  The scrapbook is full of clippings, exhibition announcements and articles about Aach and his artwork.
  - Scrapbook, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Printed Material, 1948-1988, Series 10:; (Boxes 2-3; 0.2 linear feet)
  Printed materials include clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, brochures and programs.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1954-1988, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 36-39)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948-1953, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1954-1988, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Press Releases, 1967-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Brochures/Seminar Announcements, 1951-1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1965-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Entry Brouchures, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1963-1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Audio-Visual Materials, 25 April 1975, Series 11:; (Box 3; 1 folder)
  The audio-visual materials is comprised of a 55-minute U-matic audiocassette entitled Herb Aach, made at the Albright-Knox Gallery.
  - One Inch Videotape: Herb Aach, color, 55 min, Albright-Knox Gallery, 25 April 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)